<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>malan - business</title><link href="https://malan88.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://malan88.github.io/feeds/business.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://malan88.github.io/</id><updated>2019-01-04T11:52:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>Everything I Needed to Know About Form W2</title><link href="https://malan88.github.io/everything-i-needed-to-know-about-form-w2.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-01-04T11:52:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-01-04T11:52:00-05:00</updated><author><name>malan</name></author><id>tag:malan88.github.io,2019-01-04:/everything-i-needed-to-know-about-form-w2.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In which malan elucidates the various copies of the IRS Form W2 from
the perspective of a disgruntled bookkeeper.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;In which malan describes his headache.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, like last year, come January, my boss submits to me the urgency that
we order W2 forms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, unlike last year, I had extra copies from last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, in Quickbooks, when I selected &lt;code&gt;Save as PDF...&lt;/code&gt; in the W2 creation
wizard thingy in order to see if I had enough premade forms, I was suddenly
confronted with a pdf that had 2 W2 tickets per page, and each ticket was for
a different employee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This, as, if you are actually familiar with W2’s (which, I admit, I
wasn’t—enough), is not what the employee form looks like. At least not how I
remembered it. I was perturbed. Did the IRS change the nature of the form? Are
my forms outdated (despite being blank)?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The short answer is &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;NO&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, but I had to dig quite a bit to find out, and got
bad answers from Quickbooks when I called. Literally, they don’t know jack about
the actual nature of accounting and taxation forms. Some egghead that doesn’t
answer the phones does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here is an &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; explanation, for people who have common sense, of the
nature of the forms that one must print for the annual W2 headache:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;In which malan describes the nature of the various W2 copies.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition warning"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Warning&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;I am not an accountant or a tax expert. This is not official advice and
may be wrong. It is simply how I understand it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If all you read were the Quickbooks “Printing Instructions” in the “Payroll Tax
Form” wizard, you’d see this box:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;STEP 4 — FILING AND PRINTING INSTRUCTIONS

For each employee there are six different copies of Form W-2:

Copy A to be electronically filed with the Social Security Administration by 01/31/2019
Copy B to be given to the employee by 01/31/2019
Copy C with instructions and Notice to Employee to be given to the employee
Copy D for your records
Copy 1 to be filed with state and/or local tax departments, if required
Copy 2 to be given to employee

...
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yada yada yada. Here’s the thing. This barely describes the actual process. It
implies you have to print &lt;em&gt;six&lt;/em&gt; copies—or at least all the copies that don’t say
electronically file, which would be five.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don’t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s what’s actually involved:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The employee copy is printed on perforated paper with 3 tickets: this way the
   employee gets 3 copies of his W2. These are copies B, 2, and C.&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You could print it on a paper with 4 tickets: copies B, 2, 2, and C, but
  only if you’re crazy or have employees that have to file a lot of state
  and local taxes (honestly, in Florida, we have none of that, so we’re all
  good).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The employee filing instructions should already be printed on the back of
  the form. When you order the perforated copies of the W2, it will be in
  very light and hard-to-read-for-senior-citizens print on the back. If it
  &lt;em&gt;isn’t&lt;/em&gt;, you’re going to have to print those out too, and give them to the
  employees. Believe me, it’s 99% likely already on the back when you order
  them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The W-3, which is filed electronically. So you don’t have to worry about this
   (just make sure Quickbooks files all your forms electronically).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The employer copy that gets sent to the SSA (which you also do not print
   because it is filed electronically) is a perforated paper with 2 tickets,
   upon which 2 employees get printed. This is called Copy A. This is what I
   thought was the “New 2018 W2 Form” because that’s what was generated when I
   clicked &lt;code&gt;Save as PDF...&lt;/code&gt; and the help desk at Quickbooks was too stupid to
   realize wasn’t a new form.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The employer copy that gets saved for your records is &lt;em&gt;identical&lt;/em&gt; to the
   employer copy that gets sent to the SSA. This is called Copy D. There is no
   reason for us to print it out because we save it as a pdf.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;In which malan makes his conclusion.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that’s literally it. From what I can tell, you &lt;em&gt;don’t&lt;/em&gt; actually send
anything to the IRS. You send everything to the SSA and the employee. The
&lt;em&gt;employee&lt;/em&gt; sends a copy to the IRS in order to get his return. &lt;em&gt;You&lt;/em&gt;, the
employer, file everything to the SSA. Why, I don’t really know, but that’s my
understanding and I’m not interested in actually digging into the whys and
wherefores on this one (I may have Aperger’s, but my “obsessive” and “restricted
or specialized interests” do not extend to tax forms).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that’s it! Hopefully this saves you a lot of headaches (if anyone ever
actually reads it) by providing a common sense explanation for what you’re
actually supposed to print and file.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="how-to"></category><category term="business"></category><category term="accounting"></category><category term="payroll"></category><category term="taxes"></category></entry></feed>