<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>thoughts - misc</title><link href="https://malan88.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://malan88.github.io/feeds/misc.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://malan88.github.io/</id><updated>2018-01-02T15:45:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>FOSS as High Culture</title><link href="https://malan88.github.io/foss-as-high-culture.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-01-02T15:45:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-02T15:45:00-05:00</updated><author><name>malan</name></author><id>tag:malan88.github.io,2018-01-02:/foss-as-high-culture.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In which malan introduces himself to his fictitious audience and rambles about FOSS and proprietary standards.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is literally my first post on a blog since I was a teenager.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll start by introducing myself. I’ll remain somewhat anonymous, going by
malan (malan is surprisingly popular as a username and I don’t at all get why,
so a common handle for me is &lt;code&gt;malan88&lt;/code&gt;; yes, I was born in 1988). I’m a
beginning developer (as in, mostly a hobbyist for the past few years, currently
working on a major web application project but without any formal training).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the past two weeks I’ve been messing around with various technologies, and
repeatedly thought to myself, &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; would be a good blog post. When you have to
google documentation and walkthroughs for to do a lot of things (e.g., setting
up gpg, using a web scraper, etc.), you become somewhat familiar with the
conventions of tech bloggers. A lot of them suck. Most of the tech blog
walkthroughs are written by people with middling understandings of English
(forgivable) and seem like they were written &lt;em&gt;strictly&lt;/em&gt; for SEO. It’s somewhat
disheartening. The final straw was having to, once again, search for a
comparison of technologies (&lt;code&gt;Jekyll&lt;/code&gt; vs &lt;code&gt;Pelican&lt;/code&gt;) and read a list of
&lt;em&gt;descriptions&lt;/em&gt; of the technologies rather than an actual comparison. Well,
thanks, guy, for literally copying the descriptions of the projects from their
GitHub &lt;code&gt;README.md&lt;/code&gt;’s. I could have done that myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So anyway, last night I counted on my fingers seven recent endeavors that could
serve as blog posts and decided to make one. It’ll hopefully be useful for &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;documenting my technological endeavors,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;serve as an outlet for a rather pent up need to talk about various things
   (this blog will also end up with political and philosophical and
   artistical-critical [is that a thing?] posts), and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;maybe one day serve as a semi-portfolio (personal tech blogs are all the
   rage, to which the existence of GitHub Pages should attest).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you will hopefully have recognized by now, I am a pedant. I am obsessed with
high culture in all its forms. I’m obsessed with wine, coffee, cheese,
literature, cinema, and art. I majored in philosophy at FSU. I come to
technology through rather interesting channels upon which I may (or may not)
eventually elaborate. Open source technology is another high brow subject in my
opinion. Don’t know why that is, but it is. So perhaps I’ll just express a few
of my feelings on FOSS to get the ball rolling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the fundamental things in this world that I believe in, something that I
believe stimulates growth above and beyone nearly anything government or society
can do, is &lt;em&gt;standardization&lt;/em&gt;. We might also call it platformization. The basic
idea I’m driving at is that what stimulates growth in any realm is for there to
be a commons: whether it be a standard specification or a standard platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To explain specifications, think of those for the plugs in our walls, the parts
in our computer, or even the typesetting of books. This last one is not an
officially recognized specification, but books absolutely do follow some general
guidelines, and you’d better have a good reason to break them―specification #1:
you’d better have a damn good reason to print your title backwards on the spine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some platforms are the highway system, the electrical grid, even the
financial markets. We might call the last one an institution. (Institutions are
essentially social platforms that become so ingrained in a culture that the
culture builds upon it.) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Standardization allows for competition and innovation within a marketplace. It’s
what propels an economy forward. The highway system and the electrical grid are
a common example. They’re platforms that the government &lt;em&gt;had&lt;/em&gt; to build itself
because no private entity would ever commit the funds necessary to produce it.
And yet, once it was built, &lt;em&gt;EVERYONE&lt;/em&gt; benefited, especially industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a common Democratic refrain; Obama essentially said this exact thing in
his “you didn’t build that” speech that the Republicans misquoted and exploited.
The Libertarian loves to think that only private initiative is worth
celebrating, or even allowing; he never has an actual answer to the Democrat who
asks what he thinks about roads, clean water, electricity, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s a common Libertarian argument (perhaps more accurately described as
Objectivist): &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The natural order has an equilibrium.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When humans muck about with a natural order, dictating things from the top
   down, the equilibrium is disrupted.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The economy is a natural order.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Therefore, the economy should not be mucked about with.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s the problem with this sentiment: it presupposes that the economic natural
order excludes governmental intervention. This presupposition is based on a
deeper presupposition: &lt;em&gt;that government&lt;/em&gt; itself &lt;em&gt;is not natural&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can disprove this very simply: since mankind transitioned from the hunter
gatherer stage, we have had governments. As a peculiarly social creature, with
an incredible capacity for adaptation above, beyond, and even in direct conflict
with, our genetically-predisposed behaviors, government is an integral structure
in human society and culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My point, in ragging on this Libertarian line of thought is that
&lt;em&gt;standardization&lt;/em&gt; is the perfect example of a necessary function government
serves in the economy. &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jaron_Lanier"&gt;Jaron
Lanier&lt;/a&gt; in his fantastic book &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Who_Owns_the_Future%3F"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Who
Owns the Future?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; makes an excellent case for this. A standardized platform
allows people to compete in a way they can’t when the &lt;em&gt;platform&lt;/em&gt; is trying to
compete with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specifically think of the highway system. There are tolls, yes, but just to keep
the roads in good repair. If a private organization owned the highway system,
businesses would have to factor the cost of tolls into the price of their goods
in a way they don’t now. The road owners would probably start their own
transportation company, exploit their position as road-owners, and dominate the
transportation market as well. The tolls would be exorbitant for everyone else,
unlike reality now, where the transportation industry is very competitive. The
transfer of wealth to commerce in artificially low tolls is enormous and has
fueled much of the growth of the twentieth century (beside that fueled by
advancements in technology, globalization, etc.).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now consider Google. It’s a platform, and a fairly standard one. Amazon is too.
By standard I mean that it’s a platform (product, specification, etc.) used by
the majority (if not super-majority) of people in the economy. We’re living in a
strange time in that, where in the past standards generally had to be built (or
at least heavily subsidized) by governments (think railroads, electical grid,
highway system, USPS), standards now are being built by private organizations.
This is because of the nature of software: it does not require an incredible
amount of capitol and labor to build a software product that can be used by the
majority of people; it just requires good design. The FAANGs are &lt;em&gt;absolutely&lt;/em&gt;
integral to the economy at this point, and at least three of them started in
garages. Which is awesome, because clearly the affordability of innovation is
producing incredible growth in the economy, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is that the FAANGs are all profit-seeking entities. They are not
concerned with building the best product, only the &lt;em&gt;most profitable&lt;/em&gt; product.
Because of that, they don’t allow competition with their platform &lt;em&gt;on&lt;/em&gt; their
platform, and they feel entitled to compete on their platform with those
utilizing their platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What the heck do I mean by that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take Google Play. The Google Play Store is a package repository for Android from
which we get all of our applications on our Android phones. The package
repository idea is fantastic, I love it; it is generally a lot more efficient
and easy to use than the Windows model of downloading &lt;code&gt;.exe&lt;/code&gt;’s and going to
various websites to get updates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But here’s the issue: Google does not allow any competition &lt;em&gt;with&lt;/em&gt; the Google
Play Store—that is, you cannot include in the Google Store an “app store app”
(see &lt;a href="https://f-droid.org/en/docs/FAQ_-_General/#why-isnt-f-droid-on-google-play"&gt;F-Droid&lt;/a&gt;)—and Google reserves full rights to compete with people using
its Store—for an example, see Google Lens, distributed through the Play Store,
which directly competes with the hundreds of QR Code Scanners listed in the
store.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amazon does this too: a company like Overstock.com can’t exploit Amazon’s
marketplace to leverage their own marketplace (though it’s difficult to imagine
how they would; also: they do sell gift cards on Amazon), and Amazon is
increasingly in competition with its Amazon Marketplace users (see, for
instance, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Amazon_brands#AmazonBasics"&gt;Amazon Basics&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These aren’t the only reason proprietary standard platforms are bad. A bigger
example is Microsoft Windows. While Windows may not be the dominant OS anymore
(that belongs to Linux via Android, though the technical validity of that
dominance is debatable—about the only things Linux truly dominates are servers
and supercomputers) it does still dominate the desktop pc market. Windows, I can
assure you, through my daily use, is a shithole. It literally &lt;a href="https://www.howtogeek.com/298940/microsoft-please-stop-breaking-my-pc-with-windows-10s-automatic-updates/"&gt;breaks itself
through updates all the time&lt;/a&gt;. What’s worse is that Windows obfuscates and
hides its internals from its users, which prevents those users from finding easy
help to fix. Linux, by contrast &lt;a href="https://unix.stackexchange.com/questions/308525/screen-stays-black-on-wakeup-from-suspend-centos-7"&gt;frequently breaks due to user error, but you
can easily find help fixing it&lt;/a&gt; (linked is a question literally asked today
and fixed, as well, on unix.stackexchange.com).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I’ve mentioned Linux, I think it’s time I explain how all this talk about
standardization applies to FOSS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Linux is a &lt;em&gt;FOSS&lt;/em&gt; standard platform, in contrast to the properietary standard
platforms already mentioned. No, Linux is not a standard for desktop pc end
users. It is a standard for serious computing: &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Usage_share_of_operating_systems#Public_servers_on_the_Internet"&gt;it is used as a server by
nearly every company in the world&lt;/a&gt;. This is because, unlike Windows, when it
breaks &lt;em&gt;you generally don’t have to reinstall it&lt;/em&gt;. Furthermore, &lt;em&gt;it rarely
breaks itself&lt;/em&gt;. Even Arch Linux, contrary to the memes, rarely breaks. But the
real key to Linux’s dominance are twofold:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is designed by a community of people who recognize that people build
   serious applications with it and require it to be rock solid and
   standardized.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the standardized nature of its system isn’t good enough for you, &lt;em&gt;it lets
   you do with it as you will&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the Libertarians can score one on #1: the standardization of Linux
(through the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History_of_Unix"&gt;lineage of Unix&lt;/a&gt;) was built up through a lengthy history of
undirected evolution. Programmers used Unix, so programmers built Unix up. As
they did they created a large ecosystem of Free and Open Source Software that is
standardized and well-documented. The boon to the software economy that this has
produced is immeasurable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take Git. We can leave Linux behind, since everyone knows how great the Linux
success story is. But Git never ceases to amaze me. Linus Torvalds hacked it
together over the course of two or so months in 2005 with the help of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Junio_Hamano"&gt;Junio
Hamano&lt;/a&gt; when the proprietary system they’d been using (BitKeeper) pulled
their permission. It has since become a Standard FOSS Platform. We can perhaps,
rather, use the word &lt;em&gt;tool&lt;/em&gt;. Git is a Standard FOSS Tool. And it is a miracle
tool. To quote &lt;a href="https://twobithistory.org/2018/07/07/cvs.html"&gt;Sinclair Target&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While people sometimes grouse about its steep learning curve or unintuitive
interface, Git has become everyone’s go-to for version control. In Stack
Overflow’s 2015 developer survey, 69.3% of respondents used Git, almost twice
as many as used the second-most-popular version control system, Subversion.
After 2015, Stack Overflow stopped asking developers about the version control
systems they use, perhaps because Git had become so popular that the question
was uninteresting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Git has assumed this level of dominance for several reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is ingeniously designed, representing a major leap over the previous
   bazaar of version control software, and you can realize this by reading from
   &lt;a href="https://sethrobertson.github.io/GitBestPractices/"&gt;the profusion of old timers saying it&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;IT IS FOSS&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fact that it is FOSS is key. It is because of the governance nature of FOSS
projects that developers &lt;em&gt;trust&lt;/em&gt; it. It will not release broken updates, it will
not start stuffing your repository with ads, and it will not incorporate
money-grabbing features. It’s sole purpose is to help you do your job, and be
good at it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What’s fantastic about the position of Git, not just for its maintainers, but
for all of us, is that by having a large, standardized, and open source tool,
people can do ingenious things with it that they wouldn’t with a proprietary
tool. Take the latest interesting use of Git I’ve found: &lt;a href="https://www.passwordstore.org/"&gt;&lt;code&gt;pass&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I just
set it up the other day, learning how to use (yet another standard FOSS tool)
&lt;code&gt;gpg&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have fallen in love with FOSS software because of this quality: it may not be
the easiest stuff to use, but I can trust it, practically with my life, because
it is maintained by dedicated volunteers who care about it not breaking people’s
work, supported by a plethora of developers who use it &lt;a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/tagged/git?sort=votes&amp;amp;pageSize=15"&gt;and thus can help other
developers who use it&lt;/a&gt;, and because it allows its users to do some pretty
interesting things with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of my Standard FOSS Tools right now:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Arch Linux with i3 and urxvt (Linux is a standard, though i3 and urxvt
  probably aren’t)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Neovim with which I am literally typing this (based on, of course, Vim, based
  on, of course, Vi; the standard is, of course, &lt;a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/1218390/what-is-your-most-productive-shortcut-with-vim/1220118#1220118"&gt;The Zen of Vi&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Git&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Python&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flask&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MariaDB (an implementation of MySQL)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have literally added to this toolchain the past two weeks: GnuPG (an
implementation of PGP).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even Markdown, the format I’m writing this in, which is far from &lt;em&gt;standardized&lt;/em&gt;,
though it is a standard, amazes me with its utility. (It is an open
specification, but it is not maintained except in a bazaar of implementations,
as John Gruber seems to prefer.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is something absolutely amazing about the age, pedigree, and commonality
of these tools. Notice I said pedigree. Many of these tools have such storied
histories, have had so many thousands of programmers hacking away at them, some
of them being lovingly reimplemented many times, that they have accreted
incredible utility. Let me quote a bit from Neal’s extended essay:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The file systems of Unix machines all have the same general structure. On your
flimsy operating systems, you can create directories (folders) and give them
names like Frodo or My Stuff and put them pretty much anywhere you like. But
under Unix the highest level—the root—of the filesystem is always designated
with the single character “&lt;code&gt;/&lt;/code&gt;” and it always contains the same top level
directories:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;/usr /etc /var /bin /proc /boot /home /root /sbin /dev /lib /tmp&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each of these directories typically has its own distinct structure of
subdirectories. Note the obsessive use of abbreviations and avoidance of
capital letters; this is a system invented by people to whom repetitive stress
disorder is what black lung is to miners. Long names get worn down to three-
or four-letter nubbins, like stones smoothed by a river.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not the place to explain why each of the above directories exists and
what is contained in them. At first it all seems obscure; worse, it seems
deliberately obscure. When I started using Linux, I was accustomed to being
able to create directories wherever I wanted and to give them whatever names
struck my fancy. Under Unix you are free to do that, of course (you are free
to do anything), but as you gain experience with the system you come to
understand that the directories listed above were created for the best of
reasons and that your life will be much easier if you follow along. (Within
&lt;code&gt;/home&lt;/code&gt;, by the way, you have pretty much unlimited freedom.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The Unix Hacker" src="https://malan88.github.io/images/dilbert.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After this kind of thing has happened several hundreds or thousand of times,
the hacker understands why Unix is the way it is, and agrees it wouldn’t be
the same any other way. It is this sort of acculturation that gives Unix
hackers their confidence in the system and the attitude of calm, unshakable,
annoying superiority captured in the &lt;em&gt;Dilbert&lt;/em&gt; cartoon. Windows 95 and MacOS
are products, contrived by engineers in the service of specific companies.
Unix, by contrast, is not so much a product as it is a painstakingly compiled
oral history of the hacker subculture. It is our &lt;em&gt;Gilgamesh&lt;/em&gt; epic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What made old epics like Gilgamesh so powerful and so long-lived was that they
were living bodies of narrative that many people knew by heart, and told over
and over again—making their own personal embellishments whenever it struck
their fancy. The bad embellishments were shouted down, the good ones picked up
by others, polished, improved and, over time, incorporated into the story.
Likewise, Unix is known, loved, and understood by so many hackers that it can
be recreated from scratch whenever someone needs it.This is very difficult to
understand for people who are accustomed to thinking of OSes as things that
absolutely have to be created by a company and bought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is why FOSS is high culture. To quote Wikipedia, another FOSS project:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;High culture encompasses the cultural products of aesthetic value, which a
society collectively esteem as exemplary art. It may also include intellectual
works considered to be of supreme philosophical, historical, or literary
value, as well as the education which cultivates such aesthetic and
intellectual pursuits. In popular usage, the term high culture identifies the
culture of an upper class (an aristocracy) or of a status class (the
intelligentsia); and also identifies a society’s common repository of
broad-range knowledge and tradition (e.g. folk culture) that transcends the
social-class system of the society. Sociologically, the term high culture is
contrasted with the term low culture, the forms of popular culture
characteristic of the less-educated social classes, such as the barbarians,
the Philistines, and hoi polloi (the masses).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can anyone possibly say that what Stephenson just described is not a cultural
product of exemplary value? If we take software as art, which it easily could
be, given the aesthetic value applied to code by hackers everywhere, &lt;em&gt;then FOSS
is frequently high culture&lt;/em&gt;. And this is why I love FOSS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MariaDB, from my list, is a fascinating case because it’s not at all a standard,
but it’s &lt;em&gt;identical&lt;/em&gt; to a standard, MySQL. I’ve been using it because I distrust
Oracle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which brings me back to the proprietary standards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was setting up &lt;code&gt;pass&lt;/code&gt; recently, I generated two &lt;code&gt;gpg&lt;/code&gt; keys as well. In
the process, I learned quite a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the things I looked into was how to protect my keys. If I lose them, I
lose access to all the passwords I have encrypted and stored in &lt;code&gt;pass&lt;/code&gt; using
them. So I ended up finding &lt;a href="https://security.stackexchange.com/questions/51771/where-do-you-store-your-personal-private-gpg-key"&gt;this suggestion on security.se to print them as QR
codes&lt;/a&gt;. After I generated these codes, I had to test them by reading them
back into my phone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, as I’ve already mentioned, I’m a sucker for standards. I have an Android
phone, and since I’m not a fan of installing excessive amounts of software (I am
a pretty vicious bloat-remover) I decided to use a pre-installed Google package
to scan the QR code: Google Lens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Except, Google Lens doesn’t think you’ll use the QR scanner for anything except
a Google search. When I scanned my key QR code, there was no option to copy the
text to a clipboard. So I had to go looking for something else, and settled on
Trend Micro’s QR code scanner after looking through the Play Store for a while
and seeing nothing but the general crap on offer there (ad-bloated mediocre
pieces of software written in 10 days and rarely updated so the author can
generate revenue). Then, I had to paste the text from the scan into a text
editor so I could combine it (I had had to split my key across several QR codes
because it was too much data). So I had to find a text editor. The same problem
was presented as before: there aren’t any good text editors for the phone. I
settled on QuickEdit which had too many ads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end it worked, but I was struck by how shitty the experience of getting
it into my phone was in contrast to creating it. There were no standard FOSS
tools on the Android Play store. Why? How is it that no one has made a decent
FOSS QR Scanner, or that Google hasn’t just built one into the phone yet? How is
it that there isn’t a built in text editor? Even Microsoft’s Notepad would
serve!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is why proprietary standards suck. F-Droid has multiple QR Code scanners
that look pretty respectable, and multiple text editors that look pretty
respectable. Why does nothing like these exist on Google Play?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similar problems have presented themselves to me on Amazon. Search for a quality
copy of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Winesburg,_Ohio"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Winesburg, Ohio&lt;/em&gt; by Sherwood Anderson&lt;/a&gt; and see if you can find
one. All I’ve found are, like the plethora of crappy apps on the Google Play
Store, badly-formatted copies of a public domain book generated in 10 minutes
by people exploiting Amazon’s CreateSpace platform to generate dollars with
minimal work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are competitors to these platforms, but it’s really a joke to expect them
to ever compete. &lt;a href="https://joinmastodon.org/"&gt;Mastadon&lt;/a&gt; is awesome, but I’m not sure I see it ever
taking down Twitter (we can argue that Donald Trump’s use of Twitter alone has
already made Twitter a target of nationalization). There are no real FOSS
competitors to Facebook. DuckDuckGo might be a legitimate competitor to Google,
but it’s a legitimate competitor only in the sense that Linux was a legitimate
competitor to Microsoft in the mid-2000’s: that is to say, not really, only for
power users and geeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a private platform becomes so essential to society that it cannot be
eliminated without causing serious economic problems, and yet, through
profit-hungry motives proceeds to degrade its own product, &lt;em&gt;it must be
institutionalized&lt;/em&gt;. It must be &lt;em&gt;standardized&lt;/em&gt;. Of the FAANGs, several, in
particular Google, Amazon, and Facebook, are nearing the point where their
continuous degredation is becoming so grave a problem that it will soon be time
to nationalize them. Or at the very least regulate them as heavily as we once
regulated Ma Bell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t even get me started on the telecoms.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="first"></category><category term="introduction"></category></entry></feed>